Okay, welcome to the very first lesson of this module where we're going to be
learning the very basics of the TypeScript language. Now, the TypeScript language
has what's called primitives and if you're familiar with other languages, maybe
JavaScript or maybe C# or other languages, then primitives will actually make a lot
of sense because there are things like integers and strings and bootyens and
floats and stuff like that. So, let's work out where they work in TypeScript.
Now, if you want to follow along with what I'm doing in this course, so this
site here, TypeScriptWang.org, is the actual website for learning TypeScript and
they actually have this playground here. So, you can go to this, click on the
playground and it's going to take you to this page where we can type the
TypeScript language and get it executed. Okay, so let's fast start off and the
first thing we're going to do is learn about integers and we can use the
keywords let. So, we are creating a variable here and let's say my var or my
variable and let's start it off with one. Nice and easy. So, this is going to
effectively and because we've not actually specified a type but TypeScript
is clever enough to figure out that we are actually setting it up as a number.
And we can verify that by doing a console, log and we can say type of, so the
type of command allows us obviously to see the type of a particular variable so
we can do type of my var and then once we type it in we need to hit the run
button here and you can see we get the type of number and that's again
verified by the fact we hover over it and it says it's a number. Now, of course,
TypeScript and the higher idea or the point of it is where she specified the
types rather than in JavaScript where we kind of don't. So, how we specify a
type in TypeScript is we get a variable and then we put a colon after it and
then the actual type that we want. So, in this case we're going to explicitly
set it to a number and if we execute it again we get the same thing. This time
the TypeScript knows that we actually intend this to be a number. For example, if
we now try and set that to a string, if we say for example one we can
immediately get some feedback here saying that this string is not
assignable to type number. So, you can see the immediate advantages of
TypeScript is that we get this feedback straight away even before we've
executed the code in the compiler and it compilers warning us that we're
trying to specify a string as part of a number. So, let's try and set it to
something like true and again we're going to get error because we can't make
that a boolean because it's specified as a number whereas if we now change that
to boolean, we get no error and if we execute that we get a type of boolean.
So, let's now look at a few more different types or primitives in TypeScript.
So, we learned about how to define a number and we've also learned how to
define a boolean, a boolean being true, truthy and a falsey. So, if we want to
specify a string, we can just do string like this and then give it to the name,
for example, my name, Tim and we now have a string. Now, as I said in TypeScript the
whole point generally is that we specify a type. So, these primitive types represent
single values. They're not objects and they're not arrays. There are in fact the
foundation of TypeScript's type system and we've already had a look at a few
common ones. We've looked at string and we've looked at number and we've looked at
boolean. We can also, for example, define it as type of null. If we don't actually
know what we want it to be at that point, so we can say type, my vowel, but it's
of type null and we are initializing it to null. Now, there may be of course some
situations where we want to start off with a null primitive type. And in
addition to null, we also have undefined. And again, we can specify that and set
that to undefined if we particularly want to do. So, these are the main
primitive types. We have string, we have a number and this could be, for example,
integers or it could be floats. We could also have boolean and we could also
have of type null and type undefined. Now, these are the main ones that we
need to be aware of. Now, we've looked at the main types and we've also learnt
that we have to define the types, but it is also possible that TypeScript can
be clever enough to have gotten guess the type for you. Now, this is not
generally the best thing to do because you are want to generally explicitly set
the type, but if you didn't and you did something like this and you said it's
London, for example, then it's going to guess that that is a string. But if you did
something like one in speech marks, then again, that will be interpreted as a
string, but of course, like in JavaScript, you might actually want this to become a
number at some point and that's why you want to accept that you define that as a
specific type. So, primitive types are effectively our first step towards
writing safer and more predictable code. We've learned how to declare them
and we've also learned how to type script in four system and how to fix column
mistakes. In the next lesson, we're going to explore how TypeScript decides what
type of variable has automatically and that's called type inference and it's
surprisingly powerful.